Melvin N. Gough Papers, 1919-1971
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Melvin N. Gough Papers, 1919-1971
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1987-057
30.9 cu. ft. 22 boxes; 1 folder
The Melvin N. Gough collection spans from 1919 to 1971 and includes a wide variety of materials reflecting Gough's career as a test pilot, National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics (NACA) administrator, and flight safety investigator. Types of materials include NACA and Advisory Group for Aerospace Research and Development (AGARD) reports and documents, articles, correspondence, notes and speeches, and newspaper and magazine clippings.
Melvin N. Gough
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Melvin N. Gough Papers were donated to Special Collections in 1987.
Biographical Information
Melvin N. Gough was born in Washington, D. C., in 1906. He received a Bachelor of Engineering degree in Mechanical Engineering at Johns Hopkins University in 1926. In the same year he began a long career with the Langley Aeronautical Laboratory of the National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics (NACA) in Hampton, Virginia. From 1926 to 1958, Gough was successively an engineer, a test pilot (he was commissioned as a naval aviator in 1929), Chief Test Pilot, and Chief of Flight Research at NACA-Langley.
When the NACA became the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) in 1958, Gough transferred to Cape Canaveral, where he was Director of NASA Operations at the Atlantic Missile Range for two years. In 1960, he became Director of the Bureau of Safety for the Civil Aeronautics Board. From 1962 to 1964 he was Director of Aircraft Development of the Federal Aviation Agency, retiring from government service in 1964. He died on March 6, 1994.
Gough's professional organization memberships include the Society of Experimental Test Pilots (of which he was a Fellow) and the American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics (also a Fellow). He served on the Board of Governors of the Flight Safety Foundation and was a charter member of the Society of Air Safety Investigators. He received the Octave Chanute Award for Test Pilots from the Institute of Aeronautical Sciences in 1941 for "outstanding contributions in the field of aeronautics"; the Distinguished Service Award from the Flight Safety Foundation in 1956 for "distinguished service in achieving safer utilization of aircraft"; and the Flight Safety Foundation's Laura Taber Barbour Award in 1960 for championing "through unstinting personal activity the cause of flight safety." For his contributions to aeronautical history, Gough was elected to the Virginia Aviation Hall of Fame.
Scope and Content
The Melvin N. Gough collection spans from 1919 to 1971 and includes a wide variety of materials reflecting Gough's career as a test pilot, NACA administrator, and flight safety investigator. It is especially rich in materials from his years at Langley and equally rich on the topics of aviation safety and accident investigation procedures.
The papers are organized largely according to Gough's own filing system, and there is some degree of overlap in the contents of folders. Many of the folders include manuscript materials and other items such as magazine articles and newspaper clippings. The NACA reports and other documents that are individually listed include manuscript annotations, correspondence, or other items that make them unique. Documents published before 1930 are also listed individually, whether they have manuscript items associated with them or not. Other NACA reports and miscellaneous publications are arranged chronologically. NACA reports are usually grouped by year; other publications are grouped by decade.
Arrangement
The arrangement of the collection is chronological, with all the files within a given year arranged alphabetically. Where the contents of folders span two or more years, they are subarranged by period, with all the entries for 1941-43 (for example) before the entries for 1941-44.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Christopher C. Kraft Papers, 1941-1998 (Bulk 1941-1982). Ms85-001.
Robert R. Gilruth Papers, 1936-1989. Ms90-053.
Hartley A. Soule Papers, 1950-1967. Ms87-004.
Index Terms
Persons:
Gough, Melvin N. (Melvin Neilson), 1906-1994; Gilruth, Robert R. (Robert Rowe), 1913-; Kraft, Christopher C.; Soule, Hartley A. (Hartley Akin), 1904-1988
Subjects:
Aircraft accidents; Archives of American Aerospace Exploration (AAAE); Science and Technology; United States. Civil Aeronautics Board; United States. Federal Aviation Agency; United States. National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics; United States. United States. National Aeronautics and Space Administration
Occupations:
Aeronautical engineers; Pilots; Test pilots
Contents List
- "Report of Flight Test on Moss Supercharger," 1919. (Box-folder 1-1)
- Miscellaneous photographs, c.1920-1929. (Box-folder 1-2)
- Spoiler-Aileron control system, 1921-1926. (Box-folder 1-3)
- "Fifty Hour Endurance Test on Liberty Twelve (1921 model) Aviation Engine," 1922. (Box-folder 1-4)
- "Investigation of a Pressure-Type Fog Landing Device" (Carroll and Crowley), 1922. (Box-folder 1-5)
- "Standard Method of Engine Calculations" (Caminez and Iseler), 1922. (Box-folder 1-6)
- "Control of Aeroplanes at Low Speeds" (Jones), 1923. (Box-folder 1-7)
- Official Performance Test of Curtiss NBS-4 Equipped with two 400 HP Liberty Twelve Engines, 1924. (Box-folder 1-8)
- "World Cruise Liberty Engine Performance," 1924. (Box-folder 1-9)
- "Aeronautique militaire" (Letournernir), c.1925. (Box-folder 1-10)
- Chapter V of "Airplane Design"—The Prediction of Performance, 1925. (Box-folder 1-11)
- NACA reports, 1925. (Box-folder 1-12)
- Notes on the "Measurement of Maximum Level Flight Speed of an Airplane" (Vensel), 1925. (Box-folder 1-13)
- Official Performance Test of Atlantic DH4M-2 Equipped with Liberty Twelve Engine, 1925. (Box-folder 1-14)
- "Report on Part V—Appendix to Airplane Design," 1925. (Box-folder 1-15)
- "Report on Part VI—Appendix to Airplane Design," 1925. (Box-folder 1-16)
- "The Spinning of Aeroplanes" (Bryant, advance proof), 1927. (Box-folder 1-17)
- "A Warning Concerning the Takeoff with Heavy Load" (Reid and Carroll), 1927. (Box-folder 1-18)
- Sketches of airplanes, 1927-1929. (Box-folder 1-19)
- "The Formation of Ice Upon Exposed Parts of an Airplane in Flight" (Carroll and McAvoy), 1928. (Box-folder 1-20)
- "The Effect of Fillets Between Wings and Fuselage on the Drag and Propulsive Efficiency of an Airplane" (Gough), 1928. (Box-folder 1-21)
- NACA reports, 1928. (Box-folder 1-22)
- Cowling, 1928-1930. (Box-folder 1-23, Folder 1)
- "Adoption of the NACA Low Drag Cowling...," 1929. (Box-folder 1-24)
- Daily log sheets, 1929. (Box-folder 1-25)
- "Notes on the Design of the NACA Cowling," 1929. (Box-folder 1-26)
- "Report on NACA Low Drag Cowling" (Carroll), 1929. (Box-folder 1-27)
- "Spiral Tendency in Blind Flying" (Carroll and McAvoy), 1929. (Box-folder 1-28)
- XF7C-1—data and photos, 1929. (Box-folder 1-29)
- Speed courses—use and data, 1929-1936. (Box-folder 1-30, Folder 1)
- Blind flying, 1929-1938. (Box-folder 1-31)
- Address book, 1930. (Box-folder 1-32)
- "Comparative Performance Obtained with XF70-1 Airplane Using Several Different Engine Cowlings" (Shey, Johnson, Gough), 1930. (Box-folder 1-33)
- Daily log sheets, 1930. (Box-folder 1-34)
- "Effect of the Angular Position of the Section of a Ring Cowling on the High-Speed of an XF7C-1 Airplane" (Gough), 1930. (Box-folder 1-35)
- Effect of humidity on engine performance, 1930. (Box-folder 1-36)
- Fairchild comparison tunnel, 1930. (Box-folder 1-37, Folder 1)
- "Fire and Life Safety in Aviation," 1930. (Box-folder 1-38)
- NACA reports, 1930. (Box-folder 1-39)
- Miscellaneous photographs, c.1930-1939. (Box-folder 1-40)
- Miscellaneous publications, 1930-1939. (Box-folder 1-41)
- Names and addresses, 1930-1950. (Box-folder 1-42)
- Aviation engine log book—McDonnell O2U-1 F-22 #60, 1931. (Box-folder 1-43)
- Daily log, 1931. (Box-folder 1-44)
- Directional stability, 1931. (Box-folder 1-45)
- Instruments—memo, 1931. (Box-folder 1-46)
- "...Low-Drag Cowling for Radial Air-Cooled Engines" (McAvoy, Shey, Young), 1931. (Box-folder 1-47)
- NACA reports, 1931. (Box-folder 1-48)
- Report on a flight of an NSC-2 airplane, 1931. (Box-folder 2-1)
- XSL-1—report, 1931. (Box-folder 2-2)
- "Variation in Pressure in the Cabin of an Airplane in Flight" (Gough), 1931. (Box-folder 2-3)
- McDonnell test, 1931-1932. (Box-folder 2-4)
- Smoke flow research, 1931-1932. (Box-folder 2-5)
- "The Aerodynamic Characteristics of a Model Wing..." (Weick and Harris), 1932. (Box-folder 2-6)
- Daily log, 1932. (Box-folder 2-7)
- "Methods of Visually Determining the Air Flow Around Airplanes" (Gough and Johnson), 1932. (Box-folder 2-8)
- NACA reports, 1932. (Box-folder 2-9)
- "The Nature of Air Flow About the Tail of an Airplane in a Spin" (Scudder and Miller), 1932. (Box-folder 2-10)
- Report of a flight test of a Lockheed Altair type C-23, 1932. (Box-folder 2-11)
- B.J.-Zapp flight tests, 1932. (Box-folder 2-12)
- National air races, 1932-1933. (Box-folder 2-13)
- "The Physiological Aspects of Aviation," 1933. (Box-folder 2-14)
- "Study of Factors Affecting the Steady Spin of an Airplane" (Scudder), 1933. (Box-folder 2-15)
- Visibility measurements, 1933. (Box-folder 2-16, Folder 1)
- BF2C-1—Flight test report, 1934. (Box-folder 2-17)
- Daily log, 1934. (Box-folder 2-18)
- Eaton, Warren—death. 1934. (Box-folder 2-19)
- "A Flight Investigation of the Lateral Control Characteristics of Short Wide Ailerons and Various Spoilers with Different Amounts of Wing Dihedral" (Gough, Soule, Weick), 1934. (Box-folder 2-20)
- Flight test report on XBF2C-1 airplane, 1934. (Box-folder 2-21)
- NACA reports, 1934. (Box-folder 2-22)
- Cruising control—articles, 1934-1935. (Box-folder 2-23)
- Club and technical talks, 1934-1944. (Box-folder 2-24)
- Ice, 1934-1939. (Box-folder 2-25)
- Daily log, 1935. (Box-folder 2-26)
- Hulcher camera, c.1935. (Box-folder 2-27)
- NACA "Altitude Pressure Tables," 1935. (Box-folder 2-28)
- NACA reports, 1935. (Box-folder 2-29)
- Test report—Amphibian 9401, 1935. (Box-folder 2-30)
- "Effect of the Angular Position of the Section of a Ring Cowling on the High Speed of an XF7C-1 Airplane" (Gough), 1935. (Box-folder 2-31)
- Hulcher 70mm High Speed Sequence Camera, c.1935. (Box-folder 2-32)
- "Limitations of the Pilot in Applying Forces to Airplane Controls" (Gough and Beard), 1935. (Box-folder 2-33)
- Daily log, 1936. (Box-folder 2-34)
- Landing a flapped airplane—correspondence, 1936. (Box-folder 2-35)
- "...Landing Planes Equipped with Wing Flaps" (Gough), 1936. (Box-folder 2-36)
- "Limitations of the Pilot in Applying Forces to Airplane Controls" (Beard and Gough), 1936. (Box-folder 2-37)
- NACA reports, 1936. (Box-folder 2-38)
- "Full Scale Tests of a New Type NACA Cowling," 1936-1937. (Box-folder 2-39)
- Wing flaps, 1936-1937. (Box-folder 2-40)
- "Action in Flight of the Stall Warning Device as Installed on the J-2 Airplane" (Memo to Mr. Crowley), 1937. (Box-folder 2-41)
- "An Attempt to Improve the Stalling Characteristics of a Low-Wing Monoplane" (Gough), 1937. (Box-folder 2-42)
- "Experiments with a Wing Passageway, Automatic Flaps, and Lateral Control..." (Hall), 1937. (Box-folder 3-1)
- "Handling Characteristics of Modern Airplanes from a Pilot's Standpoint" (Gough), 1937. (Box-folder 3-2)
- NACA reports, 1937. (Box-folder 3-3)
- Talk on handling characteristics of modern airplanes, 1937. (Box-folder 3-4)
- "Tapered Wings, Tip Stalling, Stall-Control Flap" (Jacobs), 1937. (Box-folder 3-5)
- Flight notes, memoranda, 1937-1940. (Box-folder 3-6)
- Landing gear, 1937-1949. (Box-folder 3-7)
- "Detailed Report of Gusts Encountered While on the XB-15 Flight December 22, 1938," 1938. (Box-folder 3-8)
- Kellett YG-1B Autogiro—report, 1938. (Box-folder 3-9)
- NACA reports, 1938. (Box-folder 3-10)
- "Notes on Stability from the Pilot's Standpoint" (Gough), 1938. (Box-folder 3-11)
- Brewster fighter tests—correspondence, clippings, photos, 1938-1939. (Box-folder 3-12)
- B-17 and B-15 maneuvers, 1938-1942. (Box-folder 3-13)
- General data, 1938-1942. (Box-folder 3-14)
- Daily log, 1939. (Box-folder 3-15)
- Bell XFL-1 (Aircobra), c.1940. (Box-folder 3-16)
- NACA reports, 1940. (Box-folder 3-17)
- Flying qualities correlation—P-40, XSBA-1, XTBF-1, P- 36A, 1940-1943. (Box-folder 3-18)
- Lilly, Howard—pilot logs, 1940-1948. (Box-folder 3-19)
- Personal aircraft, 1940-1945. (Box-folder 3-20)
- Miscellaneous photographs, c.1940-1949. (Box-folder 3-21 to 3-24 (4 folders))
- Miscellaneous publications, c.1940-1949. (Box-folder 3-25 to 3-26 (2 folders))
- Pilots—photographs, c.1940-1955. (Box-folder 3-27)
- "Measurements of the Flying Qualities of a Piper Cub Airplane [Model J3L-50]" (Gilruth, Gough, Gracey), 1940-1965. (Box-folder 3-28)
- "Requirements for Satisfactory Flying Qualities of Airplanes" (Gilruth), 1941-1947. (Box-folder 3-29)
- "Cerebral Function in Aviation" (Fulton), 1941. (Box-folder 3-30)
- "Factors Affecting Elevator Control Forces" (Trimble), 1941. (Box-folder 3-31)
- Flight Test Organization, Procedures and Crew Training (Reed and Milliken), 1941. (Box-folder 3-32)
- NACA reports, 1941. (Box-folder 4-1)
- P-51H Mustang Fighter Plane, c.1941. (Box-folder 4-2)
- "Requirements for Satisfactory Flying Qualities of Airplanes" (Gilruth—Typescript and notes), 1941. (Box-folder 4-3)
- Spitfire VA—test flight, December 27, 1941, 1941. (Box-folder 4-4)
- XP-51 Airplane, c.1941. (Box-folder 4-5)
- British Hurricane—test flight, 1941. (Box-folder 4-6)
- Martin B-26, 1941-1942. (Box-folder 4-7)
- P-40 Spitfire, 1941-1948. (Box-folder 4-8)
- Accident analysis—methodology, 1941-1956. (Box-folder 4-9)
- B-18B, B-26—crash photographs; 1942. (Box-folder 4-10)
- "Certain Comments on Cockpits by Jesse W. Lankford," 1942. (Box-folder 4-11)
- "Comments on Proposed General Specifications for Stability and Control Characteristics of Airplanes," 1942. (Box-folder 4-12)
- NACA reports, 1942. (Box-folder 4-13)
- "New Developments in Simplified Control" (Upson), 1942. (Box-folder 4-14)
- P-38E, 1942. (Box-folder 4-15)
- Supersonic air flight, 1942. (Box-folder 4-16)
- Diehl, Walter—Correspondence, 1942-1959. (Box-folder 4-17)
- "Altitude Wind Tunnel at AERL" (Witney), 1943. (Box-folder 4-18)
- Compressibility Notes, c.1943. (Box-folder 4-19)
- NACA reports, 1943. (Box-folder 4-20)
- P-38F—Flying Qualities, 1943. (Box-folder 4-21)
- "Summary of the Flying Qualities of the Douglas A-20A," 1943. (Box-folder 4-22)
- Thunderbolt P-47, 1943-1944. (Box-folder 4-23)
- Helicopters, c.1943-1947. (Box-folder 4-24)
- Helicopter notes, 1943-1951. (Box-folder 4-25)
- Brewster SB2A-1, 1944. (Box-folder 4-26)
- Daily log, 1944. (Box-folder 4-27)
- Flight instrument research projects, c.1944. (Box-folder 4-28)
- Gilruth, Robert R.—confidential letter to, 1944. (Box-folder 4-29)
- Liberator VI take-off tests, 1944. (Box-folder 4-30)
- Mosquito F.B. MK.21, 1944. (Box-folder 4-31)
- NACA reports, 1944. (Box-folder 4-32)
- "Resume of NACA Stability and Control Tests of the Bell P-63 Series Airplane" (Johnson), 1944. (Box-folder 4-33)
- Talk to Patuxent test pilots—Notes on speech and report on joint fighter conference, 1944. (Box-folder 4-34)
- Talk to supervisors, 1944. (Box-folder 4-35)
- Technical report writing, 1944. (Box-folder 4-36)
- Jet propulsion, 1944-1953. (Box-folder 4-37)
- Cockpit photographs, c.1945. (Box-folder 4-38)
- ESMWT Course—Appreciation and Prediction of Flying Qualities, 1945. (Box-folder 4-39)
- Fires in airline accidents—1938-1944, c.1945. (Box-folder 4-40)
- Fires in non-airline accidents, 1945. (Box-folder 4-41)
- "Instrument Flight Trials with a Helicopter Stabilized about each Individual Axis" (Salmirs and Tapscott), c.1945. (Box-folder 5-1)
- Langley aerial photographs, c.1945. (Box-folder 5-2)
- NACA reports, 1945. (Box-folder 5-3)
- "Personal Light Airplanes-Investigation of Stability and Control Problems," 1945. (Box-folder 5-4)
- XBTK-1 experimental navy divebomber, 1945. (Box-folder 5-5)
- Boundary layer control, 1945-1946. (Box-folder 5-6)
- Miscellaneous phone calls, 1945-1946. (Box-folder 5-7)
- D-558-1 notes, etc., c.1945-1951. (Box-folder 5-8)
- X-1 correspondence, notes, clippings. 1945-1951. (Box-folder 5-9)
- Flight operations summaries, 1945-1953. (Box-folder 5-10)
- Aero Medical Association 1945-1958. (Box-folder 5-11)
- Hydrodynamics—Seaplanes, 1945-1958. (Box-folder 5-12)
- Daily log, 1946. (Box-folder 5-13)
- "Designing to the New Transport Category Performance Requirements...," 1946. (Box-folder 5-14)
- G.E. jet propulsion in P-59 airplanes, 1946. (Box-folder 5-15)
- NACA reports, 1946. (Box-folder 5-16)
- "Stability and Control Flight Tests on the C-54 G Airplane," 1946. (Box-folder 5-17)
- Academy of Model Aeronautics, c.1946-1950. (Box-folder 5-18)
- Aircraft stalling, 1946-1956. (Box-folder 5-19)
- Aircraft noise reduction, 1947. (Box-folder 5-20)
- Annual inspection of NACA Laboratories, 1947. (Box-folder 5-21)
- Boundary layer control, 1947. (Box-folder 5-22)
- Daily log, 1947. (Box-folder 5-25)
- Hughes-Kaiser flying boat, 1947. (Box-folder 5-26)
- Hydrodynamics—Seaplanes 1947. (Box-folder 5-27)
- Langeweiesche, Wolfgang—articles, c.1947. (Box-folder 5-28)
- NACA reports, 1947. (Box-folder 5-29)
- P-80-A—Lateral control and accelerated stall reports, 1947. (Box-folder 5-30)
- "Psychological Aspects of Instrument Display" (U.S. Air Forces Headquarters), 1947. (Box-folder 5-31)
- Remote control—correspondence, 1947. (Box-folder 5-32)
- Scudder, Nathan, 1947. (Box-folder 6-1)
- Flying qualities of transport airplanes, 1947-1948. (Box-folder 6-2)
- Talks, 1947-1948. (Box-folder 6-3)
- Miscellaneous phone calls, 1947-1949. (Box-folder 6-4)
- Muroc operations, 1947-1949 (Box-folder 6-5)
- Compressibility, 1947-1950. (Box-folder 6-6)
- X-1 notes and correspondence, 1947-1955. (Box-folder 6-7)
- Handling qualities of airplanes, 1947-1955. (Box-folder 6-8)
- F-80BF-80B, 1947-1956. (Box-folder 6-9)
- F-48, 1947-1957. (Box-folder 6-10)
- High altitude and engine supercharging, c.1947-1957. (Box-folder 6-11)
- Airline accident investigations—articles, 1947-1960. (Box-folder 6-12)
- Accident reports, 1948. (Box-folder 6-13)
- Air Transport Symposium—Institute of Aeronautical Sciences, 1948. (Box-folder 6-14)
- Airspeed—Pitot-static and yawmeter head, 1948. (Box-folder 6-15)
- Daily log, 1948. (Box-folder 6-16)
- Douglas D-558-1 accident, Muroc, California, May 3, 1948. (Box-folder 6-17)
- Douglas D-558-1 accident—microfilm, 1948. (Box-folder 6-18)
- Douglas D-558-1 accident—photographs, 1948. (Box-folder 6-19)
- Lilly, Howard—death, 1948. (Box-folder 6-20)
- NACA reports, 1948. (Box-folder 7-1 to 7-2 (2 folders))
- White Sands Proving Ground, 1948. (Box-folder 7-3)
- Aircraft estimates, c.1948-1951. (Box-folder 7-4)
- D-558-1,2 airplanes, 1948-1952. (Box-folder 7-5)
- Stall warning devices, 1948-1952. (Box-folder 7-6)
- X-1—articles, clippings, etc., c.1948-1952. (Box-folder 7-7)
- X-1—memos, photos, c.1948-1952. (Box-folder 7-8)
- XS-3, X-3, 1948-1956. (Box-folder 7-9)
- Flight accidents and damage, 1948-1957. (Box-folder 7-10)
- High-speed flight problems, 1948-1957. (Box-folder 7-11)
- Lockheed model 12, c.1948-1958. (Box-folder 7-12)
- Daily log, 1949. (Box-folder 7-13)
- Fire safety, 1949. (Box-folder 7-14)
- Flight program for NACA annual inspection, 1949. (Box-folder 7-15)
- NACA reports, 1949. (Box-folder 7-16)
- Patrick Henry Airport—dedication, 1949. (Box-folder 7-17)
- Reserve officers employed at NACA-Langley, c.1949. (Box-folder 7-18)
- Talks, 1949. (Box-folder 7-19)
- XF-82 incident, Langley Field, 1949. (Box-folder 7-20)
- "Notes on Some Recent and Current Aerodynamic Research Work in England" (Kerr), 1949-1951. (Box-folder 7-21)
- Icarian Flying Club, 1949-1952. (Box-folder 7-22)
- Jets—miscellaneous clippings, etc., 1949-1955. (Box-folder 7-23)
- Turbo-props vs. turbo-jets, 1949-1958. (Box-folder 7-24)
- Weather conditions and flying problems, 1949-1962. (Box-folder 7-25)
- Fire, 1949-1963. (Box-folder 7-26)
- "Crash Loads" (Preston); "Crash Impact Survival," 1950. (Box-folder 8-1)
- Crowley party—photographs, c.1950. (Box-folder 8-2)
- Daily log, 1950. (Box-folder 8-3)
- F-84E-1RE airplane crash, Pitkin, Louisiana, 1950. (Box-folder 8-4)
- NACA reports, 1950. (Box-folder 8-5)
- Operation Portex, 1950. (Box-folder 8-6)
- "Review and Status Report of a High-Speed Research Airplane Program," (Hartley Soule), 1950. (Box-folder 8-7)
- Stall warning device, NACA memo, 1950. (Box-folder 8-8)
- Talks, 1950. (Box-folder 8-9)
- Flight safety—clippings, c.1950-1955. (Box-folder 8-10)
- Automatic control panel, 1950-1952. (Box-folder 8-11)
- Miscellaneous phone calls, 1950-1952. (Box-folder 8-12)
- MAC service letters, 1950-1953. (Box-folder 8-13)
- Overshoot accidents, 1950-1955. (Box-folder 8-14)
- Helicopter notes, c.1950-1957. (Box-folder 8-15)
- X-15, X-5, X-13, 1950-1958. (Box-folder 8-16)
- Miscellaneous photographs, c.1950-1959. (Box-folder 8-17)
- Miscellaneous publications, c.1950-1959. (Box-folder 8-18 to 8-20, 9-1 (4 folders))
- "Airplane Performance Determination At Velocities Below Critical Mach Number," 1951. (Box-folder 9-2)
- Avro C-102, 1951. (Box-folder 9-3)
- Daily log, 1951. (Box-folder 9-4)
- F-9F stalls, 1951. (Box-folder 9-5)
- Flight Safety Conference, 1951. (Box-folder 9-6)
- MIG airplane, 1951. (Box-folder 9-7)
- NACA reports, 1951. (Box-folder 9-8)
- Slidable and jettisonable canopies; list of navy aircraft delivered 1941-1945, 1951. (Box-folder 9-9)
- Boundary layer control, 1951-1952. (Box-folder 9-10)
- Civil Aeronautics Board Resume of U.S., 1951-1953. (Box-folder 9-11)
- Travel insurance policies, 1951-1953. (Box-folder 9-12)
- Inlets, 1951-1954. (Box-folder 9-13)
- Institute of the Aeronautical Sciences, 1951-1955. (Box-folder 9-14)
- Loads, 1951-1958. (Box-folder 9-15)
- B-45 accident, 1952. (Box-folder 9-16)
- "Cockpit Design and Safety" (Stieglitz), 1952. (Box-folder 9-17)
- Daily log, 1952. (Box-folder 9-18)
- Investigation of a trailing-edge angle-of-attack vane, as stall-sensing device, 1952. (Box-folder 9-19)
- NACA Committee on Operating Problems — minutes, 1952. (Box-folder 9-20)
- NACA reports, 1952. (Box-folder 9-21)
- "Some Aspects of Aircraft Accident Prevention" (Stieglitz), 1952. (Box-folder 9-22)
- Accident Survival Panel—NACA Committee on Operating Problems, 1952-1953. (Box-folder 9-23)
- Icing rate meter, 1952-1953. (Box-folder 9-24)
- B-45 crashes, 1952-1954. (Box-folder 9-25)
- Auto-pilot, 1952-1955. (Box-folder 9-26)
- Turbo-jet performance, 1952-1955. (Box-folder 9-27)
- B-47, 1952-1956. (Box-folder 9-28)
- Jet engines, 1952-1956. (Box-folder 10-1)
- Jet streams, 1952-1956. (Box-folder 10-2)
- Noise problems, 1952-1956. (Box-folder 10-3)
- Shoulder harness, 1952-1956. (Box-folder 10-4)
- Aero Medical Association, 1952-1957. (Box-folder 10-5)
- Jet transports, 1952-1957. (Box-folder 10-6)
- Aircraft seating, 1952-1958. (Box-folder 10-7)
- Ice, 1952-1958. (Box-folder 10-8)
- Temperature instruments, 1952-1958. (Box-folder 10-9)
- Spinning, 1952-1968. (Box-folder 10-10)
- Aircraft accident survival, 1953. (Box-folder 10-11)
- Annual Conference—photographs, 1953. (Box-folder 10-12)
- Daily log, 1953. (Box-folder 10-13)
- Fiftieth anniversary of flight, 1953. (Box-folder 10-14)
- "Flight Research"—memo, c.1953. (Box-folder 10-15)
- Flying saucers, 1953. (Box-folder 10-16)
- NACA reports, 1953. (Box-folder 10-17)
- Performance parameters, 1953. (Box-folder 10-18)
- Thrust indicator—talk by Vogelry and Gough, 1953. (Box-folder 10-19)
- Turbojet—water damage, 1953. (Box-folder 10-20)
- Miscellaneous correspondence, 1953-1954. (Box-folder 10-21)